<eml:eml packageId="knb-lter-and.5331.1" system="http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/data/mastercatalog.cfm?topnav=97" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.0/eml.xsd" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.0" xmlns:ds="eml://ecoinformatics.org/dataset-2.1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <access authSystem="knb" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=AND,o=lter,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>SP013</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Soil carbon and nitrogen in old-growth forests in western Oregon and Washington, 1995</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Suzanne</givenName>
        <givenName>M.</givenName>
        <surName>Remillard</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Office:  FSL 354-1;; Forest Science Department;; Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>(541) 758-8767</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>suzanne.remillard@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://oregonstate.edu/~remillas/splash.htm</onlineUrl>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Bernard</givenName>
        <givenName>T.</givenName>
        <surName>Bormann</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>(541) 750-7323</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>bbormann@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Other Researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Mark</givenName>
        <givenName>E.</givenName>
        <surName>Harmon</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>(541) 737-8455</phone>
      <phone>(978) 724-0045 ext 223</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>mark.harmon@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Other Researcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Peter</givenName>
        <givenName>S.</givenName>
        <surName>Homann</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Western Washington University;Center for Environmental Science;Huxley College of Environmental Studies</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Bellingham</city>
        <administrativeArea>WA</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>98225-9181</postalCode>
        <country>USA</country>
      </address>
      <phone>(360) 650-7585</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>peter.homann@wwu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2014-07-15</pubDate>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>Soil samples from each layer are archived at the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest.  The archive also includes finely ground samples from each layer.</para>  <para><emphasis>Related Publications</emphasis></para><para>Remillard, Suzanne Marie. 1999. Soil carbon and nitrogen in old-growth forests in western Oregon and Washington. Corvallis, OR: Oregon State University. 121 p. M.S. thesis.</para><para>Smithwick, Erica A. H.; Harmon, Mark E.; Remillard, Suzanne M.; Acker, Steven A.; Franklin, Jerry F. 2002. Potential upper bounds of carbon stores in forests of the Pacific Northwest. Ecological Applications. 12(5): 1303-1317.</para><para>Homann, P. S.; Remillard, S. M.; Harmon, M. E.; Bormann, B. T. 2004. Carbon storage in coarse and fine fractions of Pacific Northwest old-growth forest soils. Soil Science Society of America Journal. 68: 2023-2030.</para><para>Homann, Peter S.; Harmon, Mark; Remillard, Suzanne; Smithwick, Erica A. H. 2005. What the soil reveals: potential total ecosystem C stores of the Pacific Northwest region, USA. Forest Ecology and Management. 220: 270-283.</para><para><emphasis>Related Files</emphasis></para><para>Title: Soil volume determination methodology</para><para>Description: Methodology for estimating the ratio of mass of rock less than 75-mm to mass of C-bearing material to use in the determination of soil volume.</para><para>URL: http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/data/studies/sp013/Remillard_1999_FigureA1.pdf</para></additionalInfo>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/lter/data/abstract.cfm?dbcode=SP013&amp;topnav=135</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-06-16</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-09-30</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>The results of this study contribute to a total ecosytem carbon budget estimation for old-growth forests in the Pacific Northwest.  These estimations serve as potential bounds for ecosystem carbon in these forests as net primary productivity is assumed to be in a steady state.</para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <section>
          <para> An update history is logged and maintained with each new
									version of every dataset. </para>
        </section>
      </description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>notPlanned</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
      <changeHistory>
        <changeScope>Study code and preliminary metadata established</changeScope>
        <oldValue>Version1</oldValue>
        <changeDate>2014-07-15</changeDate>
      </changeHistory>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Andrews Forest LTER Program</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>3200 SW Jefferson Way </deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(541) 750-7335</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>hjaweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>Andrews Forest LTER Site</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Forest Ecosystems and Society Department in Forestry</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>201K Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
      </address>
      <phone phonetype="voice">(541) 737-8480</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>lterweb@fsl.orst.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://andrewsforest.oregonstate.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>&lt;para&gt;Field Methods - SP013&lt;/para&gt;&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Forest floor Sampling:&lt;/emphasis&gt;
Forest floor samples were taken, with a 5-cm diameter core sampler, at five points above the sampling face of the soil pit.  These samples were composited by pit.  The samples included relatively undecomposed aboveground litter whose tissue type was recognizable, as well as decomposed humified material whose tissue type was not recognizable.  The forest floor was distinguished from mineral soil by its low content of mineral material (i.e. sand, rocks, and clay).  Forest floor samples include woody debris &lt;1-cm in diameter on the surface and all woody debris, irrespective of size, within the forest floor that is not visible from the surface.  Sample procedures for treatment in the field, returning to the lab, and greenhouse drying were the same as for the mineral soil samples.&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Mineral Soil Sampling:&lt;/emphasis&gt;
On the perimeter of each plot, one or more 1-meter wide by 1-meter deep soil pits were dug, sampled and described.  Pits were located to best represent the stand in terms of slope, aspect, vegetation density and cover.  At each pit, three mineral soil layers were sampled (0- to 20-cm, 20- to 50-cm, and 50- to 100-cm).  Depth strata, as opposed to horizon, sampling was chosen because it is more repeatable and comparable to other studies.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;To ensure a representative sample, mineral soil samples were obtained by collecting material in three swaths, 5- to 10-mm deep, across the face within each layer.  For pit faces that were too rocky to make swaths, samples were collected as part of Bulk Density Sampling.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;Soil samples were kept in the shade for 4-10 days, brought back to the lab and placed in a cooler (6?C) until they were laid out to air-dry in a greenhouse (within 3 days).  The samples were stirred every other day until dry (1-2 weeks) and were then bagged, weighed, and stored until processed.
&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Bulk density  Sampling:&lt;/emphasis&gt;
Bulk density was determined for each layer with a core sampler for non-rocky soils or by excavating a known volume of soil for rocky soils.  For non-rocky soils, a 5-cm diameter x 5-cm deep soil core bulk density sampler with sampling ring inserts (AMS, USA) was used in most cases.  For soils that were too loose for the bulk density sampler to be effective (e.g., the top 35 cm at Pringle Falls), a 5-cm diameter tube was inserted approximately 10 cm into the profile face.  Inserting a measuring tape in the open end of the corer confirmed this depth.  If the depth was uneven (as with sandy, loose soil) an average was taken.  Multiplying the area of the corer by the depth of fill attained a core volume.  With both samplers, cores were taken at three locations in each layer.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;For rocky pit faces, a cube was cut (approximately 20-cm x 10-cm x layer depth), soil excavated, and dimensions of the hole measured.  The volumes of any large rocks protruding into the hole were estimated and subtracted from the volume of the hole to obtain a total sample volume, Vt.  The material removed from the hole was sieved and weighed in the field to yield material &lt;20-mm and 20- to 75-mm per layer.  Thoroughly mixed subsamples of each fraction were obtained, weighed and brought back to the lab.  The &lt;20-mm material was used to determine bulk density and was further subsampled and processed for C and N analysis.  The oven-dried mass of the 20- to 75-mm material was necessary to determine the soil volume fraction of the total sample volume, Ss.
&lt;/para&gt;</description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>&lt;para&gt;Laboratory Methods - SP013&lt;/para&gt;&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Forest floor Processing:&lt;/emphasis&gt; Forest floor samples were oven dried (70 degrees C), weighed, and blended in a kitchen blender (Braun AG, Frankfurt, West Germany) to break up material and ensure homogenous subsampling.  A tablespoon of this material was subsampled and more finely ground with an analytical mill (IKA-A 10, Staufen, Germany) to &lt;850 micro-m (&lt;20-mesh).  The Central Analytical Laboratory, Oregon State University, Corvallis, analyzed these samples for C and N content using a LECO CNS 2000 analyzer.  Samples were randomized for analysis.  Quality control samples and replicates represented 20% of the run.  Quality control samples (10%) consisted of reference material of known C and N concentration obtained from the EPA Environmental Research Laboratory, Corvallis, Oregon.  Replicates (10%) were randomly chosen samples.  Total C and N values were reported as g kg-1 at 60 degrees C.  Mass per sampling area was multiplied by C and N contents to yield kg C or N per sampling area.&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Forest floor Processing:&lt;/emphasis&gt;
Each air-dried sample was sieved and hand-sorted into the following components: &lt;2-mm C-bearing soil fraction, 2- to 4-mm C-bearing soil fraction, &gt;4-mm C-bearing soil fraction, &gt;2-mm rock (non-C bearing), and &gt;2-mm buried wood, roots, charcoal.  The C-bearing soil fractions were defined as soil that could not be broken up with a rubber stopper on a sieve.  The C-bearing fraction &gt;2-mm were hardened soil aggregates or soft, weathered rocks, which were assumed to be nutrient-rich and should be included in estimating C stores.  The &gt;4-mm C-bearing was typically between 4- to 10-mm in size.  Each component was weighed.  Buried wood, roots, and charcoal accounted for &lt;3% of the sample mass, and they were disregarded.  C-bearing fractions &gt;2-mm were only analyzed for C and N if they were greater than 10%, by weight, of the total sample.  Otherwise, the weight of any &gt;2-mm C-bearing fraction was incorporated into the rock mass used to estimate soil volume./&lt;para&gt;
&lt;para&gt;Subsamples (50-100 g) of &lt;2-mm, 2- to 4-mm, and &gt;4-mm C-bearing fractions were obtained with a sample splitter (SoilTest Riffles, CL-280 series).  These subsamples were ground to 850-?m (&lt;20-mesh) using a 20-cm disc pulverizer (BICO Inc., Burbank, California) and analyzed for total C and N concentration using a LECO CNS 2000 analyzer by the Central Analytical Laboratory, Oregon State University, Corvallis.  Samples were randomized for analysis in one of two groups: high C mineral soil or low C mineral soil.  Assignment into a group was based on expectation of either a high or a low C concentration.  Typically, deeper layers are expected to contain low C concentrations while surface layers are expected to contain high C concentrations.  The groups were run in four batches of up to 120 samples in each.  Quality control samples and replicates represented 20% of each batch.  Quality control samples (10%) consisted of reference material of known C and N concentration obtained from the EPA Environmental Research Laboratory, Corvallis, Oregon.  Replicates (10%) were randomly chosen samples from the current and previous batches.  Total C and N concentrations were obtained from the lab as g kg-1 at 60?C.  A dry weight ratio of 60 degrees C to 105 degrees C was determined on the bulk density samples and applied to these lab values for conversion to a 105 degrees C basis.&lt;/para&gt;

&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Bulk density  Processing:&lt;/emphasis&gt;
As with the mineral soil processing, each air-dried bulk density sample was sieved and hand-sorted into the same components: &lt;2-mm C-bearing soil fraction, 2- to 4- mm C-bearing soil fraction, &gt;4-mm C-bearing soil fraction, &gt;2-mm rock (non-C bearing), and &gt;2-mm buried wood, roots, charcoal.  The mineral components were oven-dried (5-7 days) and weighed at both 60 and 105 degrees C.  This provided a soil moisture conversion factor since the soils at the Central Analytical Laboratory were analyzed at 60 degrees C and values in this text reported on 105 degrees C basis.&lt;/para&gt;  

&lt;para&gt;&lt;emphasis&gt;Buried wood, roots, and charcoal:&lt;/emphasis&gt;Since the volume contribution of buried wood, roots, and charcoal was insignificant, it was omitted from the calculations.&lt;/para&gt;</description>
      </methodStep>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Models/Algorithms - SP013</para>
          <para>Please see thesis (Section 2.2) for detailed algorithms for carbon, nitrogen, and soil volume calculations.</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
      <sampling>
        <studyExtent>
          <description>
            <para>Seven study sites were selected in western Oregon and Washington based on physiographic provinces outlined by Franklin and Dyrness (1988).  These sites were located from the Pacific Ocean coast to the eastern slopes of the Cascade Range and were assumed to represent steady-state ecosystems.  Therefore, C input to the soil from plant and animal residues in the form of detritus is balanced by oxidation of SOM, in which C is released as CO2.  The sites are associated with the Andrews Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) program.</para> <para>Sampling frequency: Single sample</para></description>
        </studyExtent>
        <samplingDescription>
          <para>Seven study sites were selected in western Oregon and Washington based on physiographic provinces outlined by Franklin and Dyrness (1988).  The sites chosen for this study vary widely both physically and climatically.  These sites were located from the Pacific Ocean coast to the eastern slopes of the Cascade Range and were assumed to represent steady-state ecosystems.  Therefore, C input to the soil from plant and animal residues in the form of detritus is balanced by oxidation of SOM, in which C is released as CO2.  The sites are associated with the Andrews Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) program.  Within each site, 1 to 8 stands were sampled to estimate SOC and TN and their vertical distribution to 1-meter depth in mineral soil.  This was accomplished by excavating and sampling 1 to 3 soil pits on the perimeter of each stand.  In total, 79 soil pits were sampled to estimate forest floor and mineral SOC and TN contents.</para>
        </samplingDescription>
        <spatialSamplingUnits>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Mt Rainier Reference Stands</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-121.88700000</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-121.53800000</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>46.99500000</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>46.74100000</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>1610</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>1610</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
          <coverage>
            <geographicDescription>Andrews Experimental Forest (HJA)</geographicDescription>
            <boundingCoordinates>
              <westBoundingCoordinate>-122.26172200</westBoundingCoordinate>
              <eastBoundingCoordinate>-122.10084700</eastBoundingCoordinate>
              <northBoundingCoordinate>44.28196400</northBoundingCoordinate>
              <southBoundingCoordinate>44.19770400</southBoundingCoordinate>
              <boundingAltitudes>
                <altitudeMinimum>1631</altitudeMinimum>
                <altitudeMaximum>1631</altitudeMaximum>
                <altitudeUnits>meter</altitudeUnits>
              </boundingAltitudes>
            </boundingCoordinates>
          </coverage>
        </spatialSamplingUnits>
      </sampling>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Long-Term Ecological Research</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Mark</givenName>
          <givenName>E.</givenName>
          <surName>Harmon</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Dept. of Forest Science;321 Richardson Hall</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331-5752</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 737-8455</phone>
        <phone>(978) 724-0045 ext 223</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mark.harmon@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Sherri</givenName>
          <givenName>L.</givenName>
          <surName>Johnson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>US Forest Service ;Pacific NW Research Station ;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 758-7771</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>sherri.johnson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>sherrijohnson@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Julia</givenName>
          <givenName>A.</givenName>
          <surName>Jones</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Oregon State University;Department of Geosciences; Wilkinson Hall 104</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331-5506</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 737-1224</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>geojulia@comcast.net</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>jonesj@geo.oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <onlineUrl>http://www.geo.oregonstate.edu/people/faculty/jonesj.htm</onlineUrl>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Thomas</givenName>
          <givenName>A.</givenName>
          <surName>Spies</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>USDA Forest Service;Pacific NW Research Station;3200 SW Jefferson Way</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Corvallis</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97331</postalCode>
          <country>USA</country>
        </address>
        <phone>(541) 750-7354</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>tom.spies@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <electronicMailAddress>tspies@fs.fed.us</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Michael</givenName>
          <givenName>P.</givenName>
          <surName>Nelson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
        </address>
        <phone>
        </phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mpnelson@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <onlineUrl>http://www.michaelpnelson.com</onlineUrl>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Mark</givenName>
          <givenName>David</givenName>
          <surName>Schulze</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest; PO Box 300</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Blue River</city>
          <administrativeArea>OR</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>97413</postalCode>
        </address>
        <phone>541-822-6336</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>mark.schulze@oregonstate.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The H.J. Andrews Experimental Forest is a living laboratory that provides unparalleled opportunities for the study of forest and stream ecosystems in the central Cascade Range of Oregon. Since 1980, as a part of the National Science Foundation Long Term Ecological Research (NSF-LTER) program, the Andrews Experimental Forest has become a leader in the analysis of forest and stream ecosystem dynamics.</para> 

<para>Long-term field experiments and measurement programs have focused on climate dynamics, streamflow, water quality, and vegetation succession. Currently researchers are working to develop concepts and tools needed to predict effects of natural disturbance, land use, and climate change on ecosystem structure, function, and species composition. </para>

<para>The Andrews Experimental Forest is administered cooperatively by the USDA Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University and the Willamette National Forest. Funding for the research program comes from the National Science Foundation (NSF), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, Oregon State University, and other sources.</para></abstract>
      <funding>Data were provided by the HJ Andrews Experimental Forest research program, funded by the National Science Foundation's Long-Term Ecological Research Program (DEB 08-23380), US Forest Service Pacific Northwest Research Station, and Oregon State University. National Science Foundation: DEB0823380</funding>
      <studyAreaDescription>
        <descriptor name="Long-Term Ecological Research" citableClassificationSystem="false">
          <descriptorValue>The Andrews Forest is situated in the western Cascade Range of Oregon, and covers the entire 15,800-acre (6400-ha) drainage basin of Lookout Creek. Elevation ranges from 1350 to 5340 feet (410 to 1630 m). Broadly representative of the rugged mountainous landscape of the Pacific Northwest, the Andrews Forest contains excellent examples of the region's conifer forests and associated wildlife and stream ecosystems. These forests are among the tallest and most productive in the world, with tree heights of often greater than 250 ft (75 m). Streams are steep, cold and clean, providing habitat for numerous aquatic organisms.</descriptorValue>
        </descriptor>
      </studyAreaDescription>
    </project>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <stmml:unitList>
        <stmml:unit name="grams per cubic centimeter" unitType="massDensity" id="grams per cubic centimeter" parentSI="kilogramPerMeterCubed" multiplierToSI="1000">
          <stmml:description>grams per cubic centimeter</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="centimeters" unitType="length" id="centimeters" parentSI="meter" multiplierToSI="0.01">
          <stmml:description>centimeters; .01 meters</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="grams per gram" unitType="massPerMass" id="grams per gram" parentSI="gramPerGram" multiplierToSI="1">
          <stmml:description>grams per gram (often in terms of dry weight)</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="grams" unitType="mass" id="grams" parentSI="kilogram" multiplierToSI="0.001">
          <stmml:description>grams; 0.001 kilogram</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="number" unitType="dimensionless" id="number" parentSI="dimensionless" multiplierToSI="1">
          <stmml:description>dimensionless number, i.e., ratio, count</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="kilograms per square meter" unitType="arealMassDensity" id="kilograms per square meter" parentSI="kilogramPerMeterSquared" multiplierToSI="1">
          <stmml:description>kilograms per square meter</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="percent" unitType="dimensionless" id="percent" parentSI="dimensionless" multiplierToSI="1">
          <stmml:description>percent; a number</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
        <stmml:unit name="cubic meter per cubic meter" unitType="volumePerVolume" id="cubic meter per cubic meter" parentSI="centimeterCubed PerCentimeterCubed" multiplierToSI="1000000">
          <stmml:description>cubic meter per cubic meter</stmml:description>
        </stmml:unit>
      </stmml:unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>